You will be returned to Allah.
Thumma tur ad-duna ilallah.
Make sense?
Allah chose to say,
you will be returned to the one who knows the unseen and the seen.
What does that have to do with this conversation?
What it has to do with is,
people that look religious on the outside,
but don't actually have faith on the inside affecting their hearts.
The Death Which You Are Running From
So, the death which you are running from,
fa innahum mulaqi kum, it is going to meet you.
Thumma tur ad-duna ila alim il-gaybi wa shahada.
Then you will be returned back to the knower of the unseen and the seen.
Fa yunabbiyukum bima kuntum ta'maloon,
then he will inform you of what you used to do.
That's the last ayah for the day.
Separated, so farra taferuna minhu,
the death you are running from comes from farfara,
or iftarra, when you show your teeth when you're laughing.
And when someone moves in a quick fashion,
when your mouth moves, you'll be like,
like that's farra, or iftarra.
Farfara al-ba'een, when a camel shakes its body,
al-mafar means a place to flee or run away from.
Actually, the wise meaning is not that important.
A well-fed lamb, wow, that's a really well-fed lamb.
Ha ha ha ha ha ha ha ha ha.
I think it's called that because it's fur shakes and stuff,
because it's so fat.
But anyway, so the idea of farra is something that moves quickly.
Like quick running, quick dashing.
Escaping also is farar, farrat bin qaswara.
Right? Donkeys or mules are there,
and they see a lion coming and the donkeys run, dash for it.
That's the word farra also.
Allah says, tell them, say this,
no doubt about it, the death which you are running away from.
How can somebody run away from death?
They're not running away from death.
They're running away from the conversation about death.
They're running away from the preparation of death.
They're running away from facing the fact of death.
They're running away from that.
Allah says, you can run from that all you want.
Fa innahu mulaqikum.
Then no doubt about it, it is going to meet you.
Arabic students will notice here,
mulaqikum is a mulaaf and mulaafi lay.
Laqa yulaqi l-qa'an wa mulaqatan,
fa hua mulaqin.
This is an ism fa'il from laqa, which means to meet.
In the Arabic language, when an ism fa'il, mulaq,
or mulaqi, is used as a mulaaf,
it means it's already happened.
So, innahu mulaqin iyakum.
That would mean it will meet you.
Mulaqiikum actually means it's already met you.
It's as good as already done.
It's guaranteed.
You have to think of it as immediate.
It's already passed.
You know, the difference between
he is going to help him
as opposed to he is his helper.
When you say he's his helper, the help is already done.
If I say he's going to teach him,
the teaching hasn't happened yet.
But if I say he's his teacher,
the teaching is already happening.
It is your meter.
Not going to meet you,
literally says meter, but what's meant to say is,
it's going to meet you.
But the language used is,
it's considerate done.
Considerate already done.
That's how immediate we should be thinking about death.
Then he says,
ثم تردونه,
ملاقيه,
let's look at لقيه also.
لقيه actually means something that's thrown in your path.
And لاقه means to meet someone,
to come into contact with someone.
إلقه, like you know,
Musa A.S. was told to throw the staff.
That was ألقه يا موسى.
So إلقه was used for that purpose.
So لاقه means when you just stumble upon somebody,
you run into somebody.
This is why enemy forces,
when they clash against each other,
that's actually called تلقي.
إذ يتلق المتلقيان also.
Or إلتقاء actually.
قد كان لكم آية ونفي في أتيني التقطة.
سلطة العمران,
when the Muslims and the enemies met on the Battle of Badr,
that was في أتين التقطة.
And similarly, when the oceans collapse into each other.
مرج البحريني يلتقيان from the same origin,
when they crash into each other.
So the same way, death will come crashing towards you.
It'll just run right into you, bump right into you.
It's not going to come with like a four meeting or four warning.
It's just going to show up.
ثم تردول إلى عالم الغيب والشهادة.
Then you will be returned.
Now let's focus on the word returned.
رد is the shortening of the chin
when you pull your face backwards.
And رد is whatever organ is shrinking.
رد is a camel that drinks water,
meaning it pulls back its udders.
Now the important thing is ردود الدراهم.
Basically, if you give somebody fake money
and they give it back to you, that's not real money.
Those are not real euros.
Like you just drew an E on there and give it to me.
Then that's مردود.
It's rejected because it's not of any value.
So there's the Arabic word for returning
and there's returning when you have no value.
Return because it's faulty.
Like when you somebody ships you a product on a,
you guys get Amazon here?
You got Amazon?
Okay.
Because some countries don't get Amazon, I'm so surprised.
Anyway, it's the jihad.
It's how we should be everywhere.
Okay, anyway.
So, I don't know.
Yeah, my weird humor.
Anyway, so you get a faulty product on Amazon and you return it
because it's faulty.
That product would be مردود.
That would be مردود.
That's رد.
Okay.
Allah says you will be returned,
meaning you are going to be returned in a faulty state.
These people are being told you're faulty.
If it was just a normal return, it would be ثم ترجعون.
ثم ترجعون or تعودون or تعادون.
Or you know, so there would be different words
that were or تعادون actually.
But here تردون means you are going to be returned back
as faulty as you are.
Meaning you're not going to come to Allah pure.
You're going to come to Allah impure.
And that's inside the word رد.
You know?
Now ثم ترجعون إلى علم الغيب والشهادتي.
You will be returned to the knower of the unseen and the seen.
Why is it important for Allah to say the knower of the unseen
and the seen instead of just saying you will be returned to Allah?
ثم ترجعون إلى الله.
Make sense?
Allah chose to say you will be returned to the one
who knows the unseen and the seen.
What does that have to do with this conversation?
What it has to do with is people that look religious on the outside,
but don't actually have faith on the inside affecting their hearts.
And when we go back to Allah,
how religious I looked on the outside,
how religious I sounded on the outside,
how religious I practiced on the outside,
that's all شهادة.
شهادة means you can see it.
You can see somebody praying.
You can see somebody giving a lecture.
You can see somebody reciting Quran.
You can see somebody dressed religiously.
You can see that.
But what you cannot see is what?
Somebody may be worshiping Allah in the scene,
but running away from death in their hearts, right?
Because this running from death is not a seen thing.
It's an unseen thing.
Guys, sorry for the interruption in the middle of this lecture.
Just before you continue,
I want to let you know and encourage you
that I want you to sign up for bayinatv.com
and help other sign up,
even sponsor students for bayinatv.com
so we can create worldwide communities of students
that are studying the meanings and the benefit
and the wisdom of the Quran
and are, insha'Allah,
spreading that in their own circles.
Thanks so much.
What is going to be exposed on judgment day?
Something that could not be exposed in this life,
which is the unseen.
So notice Allah put priority over the unseen here.
He said,
and also the scene.
All both of them together.
You know, this takes us back to the letter of the law
and the spirit of the law.
Kitab is seen,
Hikmah is the unseen spirit of it, isn't it?
Alimil ghaybi wa shahada.
Fa yunab bi'ukum bima.
And by the way, also tazkiyah.
Tazkiyah, there's a physical washing in this religion,
which is seen,
and there's a spiritual washing, which is unseen, right?
So all these terms are now tying in with each other.
Fa yunab bi'ukum bima kuntum ta'maloon.
Then he shall inform you of what you used to do.
Again, coming back to the actions.
First it was what you prioritized.
What you prioritized.
Then he says,
what you used to do,
the things you were up to,
your actions are all going to be laid out in front of you.
So in other words,
Allah is now interested,
not just in our claim to our faith.
He wants to see where our actions are.
You know, put your actions where your mouth is.
Not just put your money where your mouth is, right?
Fa yunab bi'ukum bima kuntum ta'maloon.
And then lastly, just a quick comment about amal.
Amal means to do something.
And fi'il also means to do something.
But when you do something without thinking about it,
it's a fi'il.
So any action can be a fi'il.
Breathing right now for me is a fi'il.
When I open my eyes and I see you guys,
that's a fi'il.
But if I choose one person to stare at,
then that would be a amal,
because it's a conscious act.
So amal includes intent.
Fi'il does not include intent necessarily,
but amal absolutely includes intent.
So Allah is saying,
He will inform you of the things you did intently,
knowingly, consciously, okay?
Now we're coming to the most exciting part before the break.
I need five minutes guys, okay?
Five minutes, insha'Allah, okay?
We've done, we finished two sections of the Surah today.
And I'm going to give you a review of section one.
Section one was like this.
Everything in the skies in the earth does to speed.
You sabbi'ulillahi maafi al-samawati wa maafi al-arad.
You remember that?
Then he was the king, al-malik, then al-Quddus,
then al-Azeez, then al-Hakeem.
Then Allah said,
He sent a messenger among the unlettered,
who was the Ba'atha fi'l ummiyina rasoolam minhum.
Yeah?
Then he said,
Yatlu alayhi ma'yatihi, the signs,
wa yuzakkihim,
it purifies them,
you can see the connection, right?
Wa yu'allimuhum al-kitab,
which comes from the authority,
wa al-hikma,
he teaches them wisdom,
and finally he said,
wa inkaanoo min qabloo la fi'lalim mubeen.
They were utterly lost before.
Notice the bottom.
First he sent a messenger to who?
The ummiyine,
and at the end he described,
they were utterly lost before,
and then finally he ends.
Others will be joining,
and this is a favor from Allah.
Wa a'akharina minhum lamma yalhaqoobihim,
wa huwa al-Azeez al-Hakeem.
Thadika fatlullahi yubtihim yashaa, wa allahu.
Gul fatl al-Azeem,
notice in the beginning,
the opening, the blue,
and the blue at the bottom.
In the beginning,
the whole skies and the earth
are doing tashbih,
and by the end,
more of the world is doing tashbih.
Right?
Because the umma is increasing,
and tashbih is increasing.
This is a summary of which section?
The first section.
First four ayat.
Okay.
We just wrapped up section two.
First thing,
matlul ladzina hummulu tawrata thumma lam yahmuluhaqa,
matlul al-himari yahmulu asfara.
Matlul qawmul ladzina kathabu bi aayatillah,
wa allahu la yahdil qawmul al-Lameen.
They failed to carry the burden of the Torah,
and they lied against the revelations,
kathabu bi aayatillah.
Okay.
Then Allah says,
wa allahu la yahdil qawmul al-Lameen,
Allah does not guide the wrongdoing people.
Yeah?
Then Allah said,
say if you have special status with Allah,
what was that special status called?
Awliya.
Yeah?
Quli,
yah yawladzina aduhaadu,
inza'antum,
annakum awliya,
walillahi min du'l-innas.
Fataman naul maul,
then wish for what?
Death. Okay.
Then Allah says,
la yataman naulahu abadam bima qaddamat adihim.
They're not going to wish for death
because of what their hands sent forward,
the priorities.
Then Allah says,
wa allahu al-Aliyum bi-l-Lameen,
Allah knows the wrongdoing people.
Then He said,
say death will meet you,
the one you're running from,
it will meet you,
and then Allah will inform you
of what you used to do.
Yes?
So this is what we went through just now.
Now watch.
Let's start over.
No, no, no, I went just coming.
What was the first thing?
You feel the burden of the Torah
and you lied against the revelations.
And the fourth item was,
you won't wish for death
because of your past actions.
Now what are the past actions?
What are the past actions?
Fill the Torah
and lie against the revelations.
Isn't it?
The second thing He said was,
Allah doesn't guide the wrongdoing people.
And then He said,
Allah knows the wrongdoing people.
The third thing He said was,
say if you assume the status
with Allah, wish for death.
And then He says,
death will meet you
and He will tell you
what you actually used to do.
So you'll notice,
one in four,
two in five,
and three in six,
correspond to each other.
Ha, Suhal Allah.
So that's the first two sections of the Suha.
What I'm trying to show you
in these lectures also
at the end of every section,
I failed to do it in the last one,
is how the Quran is organized.
You don't sense it
when you're reading it.
You can't tell that there's actually a
structure to the Quran.
And every time I study a surah
and I work on a surah,
I also work on the structure of that surah.
How is Allah constructing the arguments?
How are they being built?
Do you see how 3D this is?
Like how are you going to,
can you speak like this?
The Quran was given to the Prophet S.A.W. as speech.
Surat al-Jum'ah was revealed at once.
He recited the whole surah to the Sahaba.
We're going to study that tomorrow.
When was the surah given?
I held back from that story
because the ayat of Jum'ah are coming.
Right?
So that, that,
the whole surah given at once,
was it written or spoken?
Spoken.
And I have to construct a PowerPoint presentation
to show you how well organized the speech is.
How structured the speech is.
This is actually
more and more evidence
how the Quran is actually not spoken.
It is written.
It's written in the law,
ma'fu'l and it's spoken by the Prophet S.A.W.
But it's not just any speech.
It's the written speech of God.
Subhanallah.
Okay, let's take our break from Ahrab.
BarakAllahu Wali Walaikum.
Assalamu alaikum wa rahmatullahi wa barakatuh.
Assalamu alaikum everyone.
There are almost 50,000 students around the world
that are interested on top of the students we have
in studying the Quran and its meanings
and being able to learn that and share that with family and friends.
And they need sponsorships,
which is not very expensive.
So if you can help sponsor students on Bayna TV,
please do so and visit our sponsorship page.
I appreciate it so much.
And pray that Allah gives our mission success
and we're able to share the meanings of the Quran
and the beauty of it the world over.