So the donkey that was trying to get rid of its burden ended up
carrying even more, which is an interesting analogy because the Israelites,
they tried to play with the word of Allah and the more they tried to play with it,
life became more and more difficult for them.
Three more complications came in their life.
Obeying the word of Allah makes life easy.
Disobeying the word of Allah makes life difficult. That is the Quran's formula.
It's always been there since the beginning.
Salamu alaikum. Before you begin this video, just quickly wanted to let you know that
so much of the work on the Quran has been completed on Bayna TV.
I want you to enjoy systematically studying the Quran from the beginning all the way to the end
in brief and then in great detail.
And to do that, I'd like for you to sign up on bayanatv.com.
And once you appreciate what's going on in Bayna TV,
I want you to become an ambassador for it and share that subscription with friends and family
and give it as a gift also. Thank you.
Salamu alaikum.
Once again everybody, salamu alaikum.
We're going to take a little bit of
closer look at some excerpts from Jewish literature,
from Jewish scholarly literature.
This is something called the Sefri Debarim.
It's a Midrash compilation. Midrash is one of their earliest scholarly works,
kind of the Tafseer work from the third and the fifth century.
And it's called an analogy of the Jews and the Gentiles,
basically the believers and the Umayyim.
So Gentiles, the Goyim, are the Umayyim to them.
Okay. And here's the analogy. Listen to this carefully. I'll explain as we go.
A man sent his donkey and his dog to the granary,
where 15 saha of grain, basically 15 bags of grain,
were loaded atop the donkey and three on the dog.
So 15 on the donkey, three on the dog.
The donkey walked and the dog strained to breathe his tongue lolling.
He cast aside one saha and placed it atop the donkey.
Then he then sent the same with the second and then the third.
This is how Israel accepted the Torah,
together with its commentaries and its minutiae.
Even those seven commandments that the Noah hides,
meaning the survivors from the time of Nukh Ali Salaam,
could not abide and cast aside. Israel came and accepted.
Okay. So the idea in this literature is that they,
humanity, the rest of humanity could not carry the burden of revelation
and they decided to be the ones to carry it.
So who gets credit? The Israelites get credit.
If you look at this ayah, Allah responds to this by saying,
Homilu, they were given the burden.
They didn't take it, they were given the burden,
so that credit is not given to them using the passive form.
On top of that, they didn't carry.
Now two animals were mentioned in this analogy.
What are the two animals?
Donkey and the dog.
And the donkey was able to carry the burden
and the dog was not able to carry the burden.
It's interesting that in the Quran,
both the analogy of the donkey and the dog is used.
Responding to this, in this surah, it's the donkey
and in Surat al-A'raf, it's going to be the dog.
And literally the donkey burden too.
In tahmed alayhi al-yalhaf wa'intatruku yalhaf,
if you put a burden on the dog, it will start drooling
and if you don't put it, it will still start drooling
because they are people of dunya.
Right?
But we'll get into the dog analogy one day
when we study Surat al-A'raf,
but right now I want to tell you about the donkey analogy.
The idea is the donkey was able to carry the burden
and therefore became the hero.
And thus is the burden of the Israelites.
You see how Allah is using something they used
in a positive sense and re-engineering it and saying,
yes, you did carry it like the donkey quite literally.
So you didn't use just a donkey carrying books.
Is what happened.
Okay?
So that's another.
Now interesting that in the Hebrew language,
in the rabbinic text, the word for the donkey is hamur,
which is basically the Arabic equivalent for what?
Al-Himar.
Okay?
And yahlmulu asfara,
asfara is the word, usually in Arabic we say kutuban.
We don't say asfaran,
but the rabbis themselves use sefer for scriptures
and the plural is used in Arabic here asfar.
So Allah is actually using words in Arabic
that are closest to the rabbinic text.
So they feel a connection to what they have
when Allah is speaking too.
So we learn something from it and secondarily,
they're hearing something.
Then another dimension of the donkey study.
The Zohar, another Talbudic text, Hebrew text,
teaches that the donkey is avi awot,
haatuma, I've probably butchered that pronunciation.
The ultimate source of impurity.
What I read today was fascinating.
They consider the pig impure,
they consider the camel impure,
and they consider the donkey impure,
but between the three of them,
the donkey is the most impure to them.
So in their literature,
the donkey is the most impure of all the three.
In addition, the Hebrew word for donkey,
chamoor, shares the same root as the word for material.
And that's why the donkey is a symbol of materialism
and crassness in Jewish literature.
Okay, now a few interesting things here.
One, the donkey is the most impure.
Look at this passage.
What did Allah do with human beings that accept this message?
What is that key him?
Look at what they believed about themselves.
They believed about themselves that because they were under the mountain,
they were pure.
And now Allah is using the analogy of the animal
they consider the most impure and saying this is,
so he's reversing a lot of the themes
that they carried for themselves.
Also, you will see later on in this passage
that they, and one of the things we saw about them
was they love life, right?
They don't want to face death.
And they will never wish for death.
And that materialism is something that we should be afraid of in ourselves.
And what is the donkey a symbol of in their literature?
The symbol of materialism,
of just having more and more in this life
and not concerning yourself with the next.
Then there was something really interesting.
I was just trying to find how is their religious tradition looking at donkeys?
Where's the imagery of the donkey, the symbolism of the donkey?
We have it in the Quran.
We have this example.
We have
So we have references to the donkey in multiple places in the Quran too,
in different ways.
But the Israelites in Egypt had sunk to the lowest levels of
This is not from my literature.
This is theirs.
This is from an article I got from a Jewish website,
Torah study website.
The Israelites in Egypt had sunk to the lowest levels of idolatry and impurity.
Outwardly, they were indistinguishable from the Egyptian neighbors.
When they lived in Egypt,
the Egyptians had their Shirk-i religion.
And this is saying that the Banu Isra'in,
when they were living in Egypt,
they basically were following the same religion.
They looked like they were doing exactly the same Shirk as the Egyptians were doing.
According to the Midrash,
even the angels were unable to distinguish between the two nations.
They questioned God's decision to rescue the Israelites
at the Red Sea,
protesting both the Egyptians and the Israelites worship idols.
But as with the donkey,
the impurity of the Jewish people was only on the surface.
Hiding a great inner holiness.
Maybe you're pure on the outside,
but there's an inner holiness on the inside.
This is actually pretty interesting.
They believe that doesn't matter how impure the donkey is,
he's pure on the inside.
Why is he pure on the inside?
Where did the purity come from?
Well, when they escaped Egypt,
they escaped a lot on donkeys.
Donkeys carried their gold, their items,
and carried all their burdens.
So they escaped.
So the donkey became a symbol of their rescue from Egypt,
even though the donkey is impure.
So then they developed this entire philosophy
that even though we are impure,
God will still save us.
Like the donkey is impure,
and he still was a means to be saved.
Right?
Now what are the Quran say,
qunubuna ulf?
Our hearts are saved.
Deep inside, remember?
It's quite literally that commentary.
Now they believe there's a Messiah coming.
So they believe in their literature.
And we already know that Allah told us
that they were told from the very beginning
that the Prophet will come.
It's in Surat Al-A'raf.
Right?
So they have some version of that.
They call that the Messiah is coming.
Okay?
Now, let the Messiah come.
And may I merit to sit in the shadow of his donkey's dung.
The Rabbi says,
if only I could just be when the Rasul comes,
and I could be around even his donkey and his donkey's poo,
that'd be in the shadow of his donkey's dung.
That'd be good for me.
Once again, we find the metaphor
of the donkey used in connection
with the messianic era.
Okay.
This is...
I'm gonna...
Let me explain this to you before I read for a game.
So what happens is they believe that a Messiah will come.
But either the Messiah will come from the sky
or he will come riding on a donkey.
Two ways.
If the Israelites are good and they're pure
and they don't do any sins and they become clean,
then the Messiah will come from the sky like a miracle.
But if the Israelites have become sinful
and they're dirty and they've made a lot of mistakes,
they will still be saved
because the Messiah will come and save them.
But this time he will come on a donkey,
but they'll still be purified.
They'll still be...
And by the way, the word is really interesting.
Now that you understand that,
the Rabbi here is saying that I'm pretty sure
he's gonna come on a donkey because we're pretty messed up.
That's what he's basically saying.
Okay.
Especially the part that even Israel does not deserve it.
Meaning if they don't deserve a Messiah,
then he will come on a donkey.
They will get the Messiah to redeem them.
It's just that the Messiah in that case
will come riding on a donkey.
Looking at the Hebrew in the Talmud,
the word for deserving is actually the word
a zekah, purification in Arabic.
Allah is purifying their concept of purification.
Because their concept was no matter what,
in the end we will be saved.
No matter what, even if we're not deserving,
the Messiah will come and rescue us.
So the word Safar, which is used in the ayah,
is actually in the Arabic language,
Safar...
I think everybody knows Safar, Musafiq, travel, right?
And Ms. Safar is a blade to remove something.
And Fara Safar is a slender horse.
Basically the idea of Safar is movement.
The idea of Safar is movement.
And the Asfah are volumes and rolls and rolls and rolls
of their books, their literature.
They didn't have books like this, like open like this.
They're rolls on both ends.
So there's two sides that roll together,
and then you open them up, right?
So there's like...
It's a long, long, long scroll,
and they write each one of them one at a time,
and they roll them together to get to a certain page.
They roll both sides of it to get to a certain page, okay?
This is actually referred to in Surat al-Tur.
One of those is...
Right?
That's actually referring to the Torah.
Okay?
So that's the word used.
It's very logical because in that kind of a design,
you have to literally travel with the material.
You have to actually navigate the text
and roll the pages as you go, okay?
So...
Okay.
Now, the imagery of sharing books.
Let's talk about that.
Let's...
There's something called...
Ataswi'l al-Fani, like the Quran paints a picture.
So now the picture in my mind is there's a donkey,
and there's a bunch of loaded sacks of scrolls,
sacred scrolls of the Israelite rabbis that are on it.
Why would the scrolls be on here?
Well, the Israelites, they moved a lot, right?
They were attacked and they had to move,
and they were attacked and they had to move again,
and one of the most precious, valuable things they had is their Torah,
which is on these large, large scrolls.
So they had to move them on the back of a donkey.
So go from one place to another to another.
Also, when one rabbi dies,
or when one rabbi passes responsibility to another rabbi,
they have to deliver the Torah.
How are they going to deliver it?
It's too large.
They're going to put it on a donkey, right?
So now the image of the delivery system,
their way of delivering a package,
the Torah package is actually by way of donkeys.
But why is that analogy being used?
It is as if to say it's just the donkey carrying the load from one place to another,
then from another place to another,
and it's just a transfer of these scrolls,
but nobody's actually reading these scrolls.
It's just an empty delivery.
It's just passing down.
So the book no longer has meaning,
it's just something that gets passed down.
One thing that really scared me about this analogy
is that in the country I come from,
and I don't know if many of you come from different countries,
but in Muslim countries,
we have this tradition that we want to make sure,
it doesn't matter if our child knows Arabic or not,
learns their Dean or not, whatever,
we have to get someone to come to the house
and make sure they read the Quran from the Fatihah to the Nast.
They did the khatamah of the Quran,
now they're done with the Quran,
they can move on with their life.
And that child, when they grew up,
they're like, my parents made me finish the Quran,
I need to make sure my child also
finishes the Quran.
They call the, did you finish Quran?
I love that phrase, it's a very deadly phrase.
Did you finish the Quran?
You're finished, bro.
The Quran's not finished.
You can't finish the Quran.
Stop mortal combat.
Okay?
But you're basically, you're done with it,
you don't need that anymore.
And it's just an empty exercise,
a ritual passed down from one generation to another to another,
where the father or the mother,
no less, no nothing of the Quran,
neither does the child,
but it's just being delivered,
like just a mindless passing down.
There's an interesting parallel in his story
that is also about the Israelites,
about how their leaders,
when they escaped Egypt,
they had lots of donkeys and, you know,
different people had animals,
but a lot of people had jewelry.
And they didn't want,
when they're walking in the desert,
they accidentally, their jewelry falls out of their pocket,
and now it's lost in the desert.
So they all collected all of their jewelry,
and they gave it to some of their leaders
to carry on their donkeys,
and to carry with them, right?
So the leaders were carrying everybody's valuable assets.
Okay?
And what happened is,
the leaders were really scared
that they were carrying everybody's valuable assets,
because if somebody comes and attacks,
they're not going to attack the empty donkeys.
They're going to,
the leaders are going to get killed first,
because the privilege of carrying everybody's money
also came with a lot of responsibility.
So what happened then,
when Musa Aleyh said I'm left to speak with Allah,
behind him, Samiri came and said,
hey, Musa's gone,
and the only way we're going to get our prayers answered
is by way of,
he came up with this scheme of designing a cow, right?
Where's he going to get the materials to make the cow?
From the gold and whatever they had left.
But all of that was not with them,
that was with their leaders.
So the people rushed to the leaders and said,
give us all our gold,
give us the gold,
we need the gold right now.
Why did they need the gold?
Because they wanted to put it all together,
melt it and turn it into a calf.
So the leaders were like,
instead of stopping,
they were like, please take it,
I don't want to be the one to die.
Go ahead, just take it.
So,
We were carried,
we were made to carry the burdens
of the good things,
the beautiful things,
being the jewelry of the people.
But the moment they told us,
take, get rid of it,
we were happily,
we just threw it away,
we just got rid of it.
There's also an imagery of,
you're given a heavy responsibility,
but you just want to be done away with it.
You don't want to deal with that responsibility.
Right?
And that's also inside,
Yehmi al-Asfara bi-samatanu qaumin
dathinakadzebu bi-ayatina.
Now,
we don't have to get into the,
actually,
now I'll just talk to you a little bit
and we'll wrap it up today, inshallah.
Now,
the analogy of donkey being carried,
to made to carry burdens,
donkeys are actually animals
that endure a lot of pain,
because human beings have used them
to go up mountains
and to put more and more
and heavier and heavier loads on them.
And donkeys do everything they can to just,
any way they can just get rid of the burden somehow.
They can just drop some,
they lean sometimes
and try to,
you know, get rid of it.
And then what their owners do is,
so that they don't,
they're not able to tip over,
they put the kind of load on them
that half of it is on one side
and half of it is on the other side.
So they're kind of,
now they double the load,
right?
And then they figure there's,
when they were carrying one,
because if you put it right on top of the body,
it's one kind of weight.
But if they try to get rid of it,
then the owner says,
okay, you know what,
I'll just split it on either side.
But then the owner realizes,
I could put a lot more on here now.
Right?
So the donkey that was trying to get rid of its burden
ended up carrying even more,
which is an interesting analogy
because the Israelites,
they tried to play with the word of Allah
and the more they tried to play with it,
life became more and more difficult for them.
Three more complications came in their life.
Obeying the word of Allah makes life easy.
Disobeying the word of Allah makes life difficult.
That is the Quran's formula.
It's always been there since the beginning.
That's why Allah says,
You read Allah will be
You kafifa al-kum.
Allah intends to make your burden
easy, lighter.
Wa quli qad ilsanu dha'ifa
Human beings were created weak.
Marriage was made easy.
Divorce was made easy.
Inheritance was made easy.
Prayer was made easy.
Zakat was made easy.
All matters in Islam are actually
things that make life easy.
And all the things you'll notice,
all the things that are prohibited in Islam,
like alcohol or gambling or any,
all of them are either addictions
or if you stay in them,
they create a lot of difficulties.
Like even if they feel good in the moment,
they will create like enormous
long-term burdens and difficulties.
So the thing, the law of Allah,
the purpose of the law of Allah
is actually to make the burden lighter.
But when they didn't follow the exact law of Allah,
the burden kept getting heavier and heavier
and heavier and heavier and heavier
on the like ad-danki that is being made
to carry so much load.
There's also a pretty storm criticism.
Ad-danki doesn't understand what it's carrying.
But the rabbis did understand
the Torah.
They didn't.
So there's a contradiction in the parallel.
The animal doesn't understand what it's carrying.
But the scholars of the Torah
understood what they were carrying.
Allah is saying that kind of understanding
is as good as not understanding at all.
Scary that you can know something,
but if you know the word of Allah,
but you're not benefiting from it,
you're not living by it,
it's Kitab and not Hikmah, right?
Then there's the word of Allah.
Then there's no difference between an animal
who doesn't know it at all.
There's, in other words, there's real,
there's the real knowing of the book
and there's the artificial knowing of the book.
And we have to be afraid that our relationship
with the Quran will no longer be real,
it will become artificial.
That's the scary part.
Which is why I want to,
before I end this session,
I want to take you back to the second ayah
for a quick moment.
We, you know, the recitation of the Quran,
the recitation of the Quran should be beautified.
And if you don't know how to recite the Quran with the Jwi,
and you don't know how to recite the Quran
melodiously, for example,
this is something you should work on for yourself.
You should, one, be listening.
If you like listening to a recitation of the Quran,
that Haqqari that you like,
somebody that you enjoy listening to,
listen to them, put them on and listen to them,
make a habit out of listening to the Quran.
While you're the study of the Quran
and the engagement with the Quran,
that all has its purpose.
But listening to the recitation of the Quran
has its own purpose.
But ultimately, even the listening should be replaced
with what?
With yourself reciting the Quran.
And you have to,
you have to try to work on that
to the point where you start enjoying reciting the Quran.
And when you do that,
that is actually when you're starting
to have a real relationship with the Quran.
People say,
I want a relationship with the Quran.
The relationship with the Quran
is not just going to come from study.
That's going to be an intellectual relationship.
But a real relationship with the Quran,
the emotional bond with the Quran,
your heart is attached to the Quran,
that's going to come from recitation.
That's not going to come from the Seer study.
That's not going to come from listening to lectures.
That's another department,
two different departments, you know?
And that deserves its own attention.
I can tell you,
the study of the Quran,
when these weeks,
when I'm teaching Quran week,
I'm all up in Quran study.
Right?
At the moment this week is done,
I'm not studying any Quran.
I'm just reciting.
Because what I see in myself is,
if you focus too much on the mind,
then the heart starts to suffer.
And then you have to replenish that with the heart.
And you have to,
the recitation actually helps the heart.
It helps, it calms me,
it gives me peace.
You know?
It makes me feel connected to Allah,
so Allah makes me feel connected to the Quran.
And then when I recite it,
then it makes me more curious,
and it brings me back to what?
The study.
And then the study makes me want to go back to recite.
And there's this kind of,
there's the
يطلوع عليهم آياته ويزكيهم
on the one side,
and then يعدهم الكتابة والحكمة
on the other side.
And that should be every person's life,
like a little bit of time,
and the recitation,
a little bit of time in the study,
and you're kind of,
you're building your relationship
on both fronts with Allah's Book.
And don't underestimate the value of one or the other.
Like people say,
people get on extremes and say,
oh, you don't even understand what you're reciting.
Why are you even reciting it?
Or why should I even go pray?
I don't even understand what's being said.
Isn't it more important that I just read the translation?
That's cool for here.
But the recitation,
exact words given by Allah,
that's good for what?
For here, that's for the Qaylim.
So those are two separate things
that we have to work on simultaneously.
The advantage that the Arabs had,
the Ummeyin,
the first Ummeyin had,
was when they heard the Quran,
they were understanding it at the same time.
So their recitation,
and their thinking about it,
was happening simultaneously.
Now the rest of us are not Arabs.
So we got until we learn Arabic,
we got to separate those two projects.
Until, and it evolved ourselves until the time
where those two projects can work hand in hand together.
Right?
So,
بيت سمثاً والقوم الندينة كذبوا بيعيات الده
What a terrible example of the nation
that lied against the ayat of Allah.
The scary part here is,
تقذيب,
lying against the ayat of Allah
is a phrase used for Mushriqeen.
It's a phrase used for kafirin.
It's a phrase used for those who rejected the Prophet,
rejected the Quran, rejected Revelation.
And Allah is saying,
the people who were scholars of Revelation,
He considers them people who lied against the Revelation
that they believed it.
You know?
They say,
نُوْمِنُوْ بِمَا وُنْزِلَ عَلَيْنَا
Allah says,
وَيَكْفُرُونَ بِمَا وَرَأَهُوا
They say,
We believe in what we have.
We don't have to follow yours.
We already believe in what?
We have.
And Allah says,
No, they deny what is with them.
They disbelieve in even what is with them.
I was actually,
for a long time I thought this is just,
you know,
Allah is saying this,
but there's no way to prove it.
That they actually know that the Quran
is also the word of Allah.
Until I heard about Rabbi Abramson
on Facebook actually,
and I follow him.
I look up what he says every now and then.
Great scholar of rabbinic tradition,
a Rabbi,
and also a student of Hadith actually.
So he's an Arabic student of Hadith.
And he's answered many Muslim questions about the Quran
and several Orthodox Jewish scholars
believe that Muhammad,
sallallahu alayhi wa sallam,
is in fact a messenger of Allah.
According to them,
they have a checklist of how many things,
how many proofs do you need
before you declare someone a prophet of God.
They,
the prophet said according to them,
meets all of the criteria,
all of them.
So they believe him,
a good number of Orthodox rabbis,
believe him to be a messenger of Allah even today,
but they say he's just not for us.
He's for everyone else.
He's great for everyone else.
We have what we have.
We're in a different category.
You see?
To me, that's mind blowing.
It's mind blowing that they come that far
and then they step back.
But they do,
and they're not even hiding it anymore.
They actually say it.
Say it, you know?
So,
I'll make a post about that soon.
I'll put it on Facebook.
I'll share some of his posts with you guys.
So you know who I'm talking about,
inshallah.
But,
What is Allah saying?
If you deny one ayah,
it's the same as you denying all of it.
You can't say,
oh, I like Moses,
but I'm not a fan of Jesus.
You can't do,
oh, I like Moses and Jesus.
Muhammad, you know,
you can't do that.
You can't say,
oh, I like Jibreel,
but Amikaela,
you know,
so if you start picking and choosing,
Allah says,
من كان عدوة الناهي ورسولي وجبريلا وميكال
فإن الله عدوة الكافري
That's why at the end of Surat Al-Baqarah,
whoever becomes an enemy to Allah
and his messengers and Jibreel and Mika'al,
then Allah is an enemy to all those who disbelieve.
Meaning,
this is one unity.
Allah,
the source,
the angels,
the delivery,
the messengers,
the recipient.
This one chain.
It's a supply chain.
Yeah.
You deny any part of this supply chain,
the chain is broken.
That it doesn't count.
That's why we say at the end of Surat Al-Baqarah,
Allah makes us say
We don't distinguish between any of his messengers.
We accept all of them.
And that is the,
that was the demand made from them.
The first kufr they did,
according to the Qur'an,
the first major kufr that the Israelites did
was actually against Isa A'ab,
when they denied his Rasada.
They've committed many crimes before,
killed prophets before,
did terrible crimes.
Those are,
those have been already mentioned.
But the major crime
with their first kufr,
the takdeeb of the
Kitab of Allah completely,
there's one thing to accept it
and play games with it.
It's another to just deny it completely,
was what was sent to them
through Isa A'ab.
And then the second time
is with Muhammadur Rasulullah,
Sallallahu Alaihi Wasallam.
This is big sa,
and finally,
the last part
and the scariest part,
is the Qulamah of the Alibeen.
Allah does not,
Allah does not guide
wrongdoing people.
Allah did not mention this in the past tense.
He mentions this in the present and future tense.
Why?
Because the whole point of this example is not
Allah does not guide them.
Allah will not guide them.
Or Allah will not guide those
who were given the Torah.
That's not what he said.
Allah said,
Allah didn't say Allah will not guide the Jews.
That's not what he said.
He said Allah will not guide
the wrongdoing people.
Now the wrongdoing people
is an adjective, isn't it?
Which noun fits this adjective?
Any noun could fit this adjective.
You and I could become
Al-Kalmahbadi Meen.
They could be Al-Kalmahbadi Meen.
Christians could become Al-Kalmahbadi Meen.
Anybody could become Al-Kalmahbadi Meen.
So at the end,
this warning at the end,
is to come back,
this is called the Jadid.
We went into the example,
now we're out of the example.
Now we're back to the universal principle.
Don't become Al-Kalmahbadi Meen.
Because I will not guide you if that happens.
Aya 2 was about how he gave guidance.
And Aya 3 is when will people lose guidance, isn't it?
That's the relationship between 2 and 3.
2 was he sent a messenger.
This is how he delivered guidance.
And now Allah is saying,
Yep, and now if you do this,
then even if you have the book,
even if you have the book,
even if you become scholars of the book,
you'll just be donkeys that will not be guided.
You won't have it,
you'll have it without you,
you'll be deprived of it
while having it at the same time.
That is the fear that Allah has put inside the ummah,
that they shouldn't develop that kind of tradition
with their book.
Or you know,
I go around the world,
I see many madrasas of Ta'feel of the Quran.
I'm gonna close this,
just talk to you guys.
Ta'feel of the Quran.
Meaning kids memorizing the Quran,
all over the world.
Well, Allah protect these kids, right?
Those madrasas,
instead of criticizing them,
that these kids are memorizing the Quran
and doing nothing else,
we need to make a campaign
that these kids that are memorizing the Quran
should also be given the tools
to understand what they've memorized.
Can you imagine the hundreds of thousands,
if not millions of kids
that are memorizing the Quran,
all become
duaat of the Quran.
All can,
they can speak about any eye of the Quran intelligently.
At a basic level.
They know what it means,
they can share it with somebody else.
Can you imagine just these millions of Quran carriers
walking around?
You know?
And they don't even have to open it.
It's already inside.
They're carried.
So I don't criticize those institutions.
I say,
hey,
you've done the hard part already.
All we gotta do now is make sure
that we don't raise a generation
that looks like
khimar yahmi al wasfara,
we don't want this.
And I'm not calling those children this,
but this is not a fear
that they just have these words
and they have no connection
with what they mean.
And when you ask them what they mean,
also don't ask somebody else.
That's not me.
I just memorize it.
Oh no, no.
There's no excuse.
The Oma has no excuse.
And you can't,
we can't even make the excuse,
oh, it's Arabic.
Arabic is so hard, bro.
You learn English.
You learn German.
But didn't you?
Muslims moved to Russia.
What did they learn?
Russian.
I met Muslims in China.
They learned Chinese.
You can learn Chinese.
You can learn Arabic is so hard, though.
Really?
You, you can,
you can read blockchain.
You can read code.
You can read that,
but you can't learn Arabic.
You know, this is not an excuse.
It's just we haven't put the emphasis on it
because we started believing
reciting the Quran is enough.
Hearing it's beautifully recited is enough.
That is the relationship we need with the Quran.
That is what we should put our money and time
and resources in.
If that same money and time and resources and energy
was going into memorizing Quran
and understanding the Quran at the same time,
you would look like a different Oma.
I honestly believe we would look like a different Oma.
There's no way that our millions of kids
would carry the Quran in their heart
and it wouldn't affect their hearts.
You know?
It wouldn't affect our overall comprehension
and when someone says something crazy,
immediately, wait, Allah says something else.
We'd be a wikipedia Oma.
Right?
So every time something wrong comes,
there's a surge of correction
because everybody's carrying the Quran.
Everybody's carrying it,
which is why I think there's a lot of potential
in the next generations now.
What I saw, the Oma has been through
a very depressing situation for a long time,
but what I see now,
Allah o Adam, I see a rise.
I just, wherever I go, I see a rise.
I see a new generation of Muslims
that are more curious,
more investigating, more thoughtful.
I meet 13 year olds that are smarter
than I was when I was 25.
Very commonly, they come and ask questions all the time.
I was really stupid at your age.
Like, you're way too smart for this age.
You know, there's a higher level of intelligence,
there's a higher level of curiosity.
Yes, the dumb people are dumber
than ever before,
but arguably smart people are also
smarter than ever before.
There's more potential now than ever before.
And I see a huge opportunity.
I see a massive, massive opportunity,
something within our grasp.
It's low-hanging fruit.
It's not some impossible dream.
And to me, that is what is,
inshaAllah, going to reverse this tide
of the majority of us just becoming disconnected
with the word of Allah.
Look at that.
Look at how strongly Allah criticized those
who didn't live up to the Torah.
Doesn't the Quran deserve much more than the Torah?
The final word of Allah meant for all of humanity,
the great word of Allah,
the exact word of Allah,
doesn't it deserve so much more?
And if we fall, if Allah is criticizing them
with the analogy of the Himmah,
and don't we deserve much worse criticism
if we fall short?
That's the scary thing.
So may Allah Azza wa Jalla make us a people
that rise above this state that we're in
and we become part of the solution.
We become part of raising generations
that are going to be deeply, deeply connected
with the word of Allah
and have a real loyalty to its messenger,
sallallahu alayhi wa sallam.
Okay, so I'm going to conclude here, inshaAllah.
Salaamu alaikum everyone.
There are almost 50,000 students around the world
that are interested on top of the students we have
in studying the Quran and its meanings
and being able to learn that
and share that with family and friends.
And they need sponsorships,
which is not very expensive.
So if you can help sponsor students on Bayna TV,
please do so and visit our sponsorship page.
I appreciate it so much
and pray that Allah gives our mission success
and we're able to share the meanings of the Quran
and the beauty of it the world over.