Allah is so powerful he doesn't have to become visible in how he exerts his power
Lotiful limayasha, he's subtle in how he does things
Delicate in how he does things nearly unnoticed in how he does things
You know and some things is very obvious and some things is very delicate and invisible
And that's actually one of the great manifestations of the might of Allah
As-Salaamu Alaykum Wa Rahmatullah Wa Barakatuh
Bismillah wa Salatu wa Salamu Ala Rasulullah Wa Ala Aali wa Sahbihi Al-Juma'in
Ma ba'at fa a'oudu billahi bin al-Shaytan al-Rajim
Bismillahir Rahmanir Rahim
Yusabbihu Lillahi Ma fis Samawati Wa Ma fis Al-Ardil Maliki Al-Quddus Al-Aziz Al-Hakeem
Rabi Al-Shahli al-Sadri wa Yassili Amri
Wa Halu Al-Aukta Tam Billi Saniyya Fqahu Qawli
Amin Ya Rabbi Al-Alamin
Once again everyone, As-Salaamu Alaykum Wa Rahmatullah Wa Rahmatullah Wa Rahmatullah
We're gonna start talking about the name Al-Malik of Allah
So Allah is uniquely described himself in this Surah
On the opening ayah with four names Al-Malik Al-Quddus Al-Aziz Al-Hakeem
Many places in the Quran Allah mentions two of his names together
Like Al-Aziz Al-Hakeem, Ghafurun Rahim, things like that, right?
So this Surah is unique because the opening has four names together
So that is a special feature of this Surah
So the first of those names is Al-Malik
It's used rarely in the Quran, it's not as common as you might think
But let's talk about a little bit of where the word Malik comes from
So the word Malik, or the verb Malika
Actually has to do with making something hard
Like you know when you make the dough and the bread
And the dough becomes tougher
That's actually Tamlik of the bread
From it also comes the idea of the Milak
Something is the foundation of a building
Or something that you build on top of
Madakut Tariq is the middle of the road
Meaning the most firm part of the road
Qawaimukulli Dabbatin Mulukuhu
The feet of an animal that it stands firm on
They're also called the Muluk of it
Meaning all of it has to do with firmness, toughness, stability
That sort of thing, these are the meanings in it
When you have control over something
That's called Malika Anshayt
Or you know command over something is a Malika
Malika Nafsahu to have control over yourself is Mulkuh Nafs
If you're able to control your emotions
Or if you're able to control your behavior
So these are the word keeps having to do with Kingdom
Or actually control and power and stability
These are the recurring themes inside of the word Mulk
Then comes the idea of when you hold something firm in your hand
Then you have Mulkuhu over it
So it's something firmly or grasping something firmly
So it's actually interestingly also used when a man is very possessive over his wife
Then they actually say Malika Al-Mar'a
It doesn't mean he owned the woman
It actually means he's very possessive over her
Or very dominating or controlling over her, etc
Now, how is this used for Allah in the Quran?
First of all in the Fatiha we have two readings Malik-e-Omiddin and Malik-e-Omiddin
So Malik and Malik are two different words
So let me help you understand them in easy language
Malik means owner
So I'm the Malik of this laptop
The Malik of this laptop
But I'm definitely not the Malik of this laptop
That would be a little bit dramatic of me
Because I am the owner of this laptop
But I'm definitely not the sovereign king ruler of this laptop
Okay, so you can own a car, you can own a pen, you can own a shirt
But you can't declare yourself the sovereign king of your t-shirt
It doesn't make sense
So the idea of kingdom is vast
The word Malik is used for vast territory
That you can be the king of an island
You can be the king of a country, king of an empire, etc
Right?
In America we use the king very little
This is the king of pizza
And this is the king of tires
Come to the Tire King for your special discount, etc
So they use these words king uselessly
But the idea of kingdom is actually a vast empire of some sense
Interestingly, a phrase in the Qur'an combines both of these concepts
Malik-e-Mulk
Qulillahumma, Malik-e-Mulk
Right?
Which is two different concepts
It actually means the owner of kingdom
So the word for ownership is milk
So it would be Malik-e-Mulk
Or Malik-e-Mulk
So one would be the owner of ownership
Or the king of kingdom
But Allah fused the two phrases together
He said Malik-e-Mulk, which means the owner of kingdom
So let's understand the difference between owner and king a little bit deeper
When I own something
Like if I own this machine
That I'm engaged with it
I'm taking care of it
I have more direct access to it
But if I'm the king of a nation
Do I have control over everyone living under my nation?
No, because generally I have authority
But I don't have direct reach to everything that's under my kingdom
I have to have advisors, governors
Who have to have their own soldiers or their departments
And those departments have lieutenants and so on and so forth
Until you get to, for example
A government is at the top
You have the president or something
And the old days you have a king
And at the bottom you have somebody working at the post office
But the post office worker works for a department
Which answers to a department
And eventually goes up all the way to the ultimate authority
You understand?
But in that little department
He acts like he's the king and the post office guy
But the idea is that he's the Malik
Doesn't do direct engagement
But the Malik does
The Malik does direct engagement
Allah takes both of those names and fuses them together
When he says Malik al-Mulk
Another name of Allah is Malik in the Quran
في مقعد صدق عند مليك مقتد
Malik means the one who will always stay the king
It's a some sifah
So the one who will remain king forever
Because kingdoms
What comes in your mind when you think of kingdom?
Somebody inherited the kingdom
Or somebody usurped or took kingdom by force
That's how you get kingdom
And eventually that king whoever took it is going to get old
And he's going to either have a brother or a son
Or a younger son versus an older son
Some drama is going to happen
Right? And kingdom is going to get passed on
The king cannot hold on to the kingdom forever
Allah's name is also Malik
Which means the forever king
The forever king
That's one of Allah's names
Then the interesting thing about the word Malik
When it comes on its own
Al Malik
It's both times associated with
Two times associated with Al Qudus
The next name that's coming
Al Malik Al Qudus is here
Al Malik Al Qudus will also come in Sul'Tul HaShar
Okay? So
Al Malik Al Qudus is Salam al-Mu'min
Right there
And of course there's also the phrase
فَتَعَالَ اللَّهُ الْمَلِكُ الْحَقْ
Which means how high Allah is
The ultimately deserving king
The king who is the king who deserves to be the king
Also because when you think of kingship
You always sometimes think of a person who doesn't deserve it
Right? They don't truly deserve to be the king
They're the useless prince that became the king
Or these people they took over power
And they unjustifiably took over the kingdom
And therefore they became the king
But they're not the rightful king
You know so many movies you haven't seen because you're Islamic
Are about fights against the unrightful unjustified king
And the rightful king comes and wants to
Claim his you know make his claim on the throne
And there's a whatever drama happens right?
So the idea of Al Malik Al Haq is the rightful king
And Allah mentions over and over again in the Quran
لَهُ الْمُلْكُ
He owns all kingdom
It's a very interesting concept
Allah himself is the king
But then he says he owns all kingdom
What's the difference between these two?
One is about Allah himself
He's the king
The other is every king that ever existed
Is actually owned by Allah
He owns all kingdom
Like he owns he decides when they live and when they die
Here they are thinking they decide when someone lives and someone dies
But actually Allah is deciding whether they live and whether they die
Which is why Allah says
لَهُ الْمُلْكُ وَلَا اُلْحَمْ
يُحْيِي وَيُمِي
Like in the Hadid
لَهُ الْمُلْكُ وَا الْسَمَوَاتِ وَالْأَرْضِ
يُحْيِي وَيُمِيْت
He owns the kingdom of the skies and the earth
He gives life and he gives death
You're distracting them
They're looking at you
There's so many people looking at you right now
It's like I wanted to look at you
That's what happens
Ha!
I keep an eye on you people
Okay anyway
Let's do this Allah
See I have no problem with awkward moments
I have this
It's okay
It happens
It was one time I was giving a khutbah
This guy got a phone call
First row
Okay if you're gonna pick up your phone
At least be in the back row
He's in the first row
And you know some people when they get a call
Long distance call
They think it's still 1975
Where they have to talk extra loud
Cause you're going across the ocean
It's a WhatsApp call dude
Everybody gets the same message
Like it's not a different
Hello is everything okay?
Yeah
How's uncle?
Uncle's good
Yeah over and out
It's not a walkie talkie man
Saqqa al khutbah
The guy that started doing this
And I was like in the middle of the khutbah I was like
I just stopped my khutbah
I was like this is a really interesting conversation
Let me just finish
So he took a full 90 seconds
Finished this conversation
I was like is uncle okay?
He goes yeah it's okay
I was like okay
Okay
Anyway
So al-Medic actually has to do with rule
Ownership and control
Let's talk about these three concepts
Rule ownership and control
Is it possible that you can have rule without ownership?
For example the government you live under has rule
But does it have ownership of your property?
It doesn't
Right so there's some level of your own ownership
Even though somebody else has the rule
You have
And the flip can happen
You can have ownership but you don't have what?
Rule you have ownership over your car
But you don't have the rule over it to drive however you want
Okay
You can have ownership over your house
But there are rules in your neighborhood
And you cannot modify it however you want
You cannot make whatever changes you want
There are regulations in place
You have ownership but you don't have rule
So those two things can exist separately
You can also have rule without control
The government in the country can have rule
But does crime still happen?
Yeah so they have rule but they don't have control
Okay
Forget crime even in a government
There's a president, there's a vice president, there's a chancellor
There's whatever other roles
Does the president the higher level authority
Does he necessarily control the behaviors of everybody in his own office?
No
In fact forget government even in a business
If many of you run a business
You are the owner of the business
So you have the rule
And your own employees are not under your control
Like the moment you look away
Things are happening and even when you're looking
They're looking straight at you and doing the wrong thing
You're like
Why did I hire you?
So anyway
So you can have owners, you can have rule without control
You can also have ownership without control
A man can own a horse for example
And the horse is not under his control
Right?
It's not under your control
And in fact one of the most interesting examples of ownership
Supposed ownership is our body
Right?
If you think of one thing that you have complete autonomy over
It's your own body
But I don't have control over
You know things like my cholesterol
Or you know my heart rate
Or you know I can't control those things
The way that I would like to
I cannot control aging
The way I would like to
It's not under my control
You know
My if your eyesight is getting weaker
You can't control that
You know you can't control your allergies
So you don't even actually have
We have some level of ownership over our bodies
But we actually don't really have control
So
When Allah describes himself as
Ultimately al-malik
He's taking all three things at once
He's taking rule
He's taking ownership
And he's taking
Control
Which in the real sense
Nobody else can have
You can't have all three
Yourself
It's impossible
And that's why he's al-malik
The ultimate
He's not just a king
He's the ultimate king
Now the other interesting thing
In another ayah in Ali-Imran
Allah did something really remarkable
When it comes to kingdom
Or ownership
Allah separated it from dignity
He says
Tu'til mulkaman tasha
Watanzi'u'l mulkaman tasha
He separated those two concepts
In other words
Allah says
We tell Allah
We ask
We declare to Allah
You give kingdom to whoever you want
And you take it away from whoever you want
And you honor whoever you want
And you humiliate
Whoever you want
You know what that means?
Sometimes Allah will take kingdom away from someone
But they still have honor
Sometimes Allah will give kingdom to someone
But they have humiliation
Separate concepts
In this world we think whoever has kingdom
Has honor
And whoever has no kingdom
Has been humiliated
But Allah says
No, that's a separate thing
That he gives and takes away
And honor and humiliation
Are separate things that he gives and takes away
So for example
Ibrahim alayhi salam has no kingdom
But he's honored
And Namrud has a lot of kingdom
But he's humiliated
You understand
Fir'aun has a lot of kingdom
But he's humiliated
And Musa alayhi salam has no kingdom
But he's honored
So he can give and take as he wants
And then he can give both to someone
He can give honor and kingdom
Like Dawud alayhi salam
Suleiman alayhi salam
He can give both to them
Or he can take both away from them
Like Ayyub alayhi salam
Or he can be humiliated by his family
And even tested in that way
Or Yusuf alayhi salam
He's being humiliated by people
Being falsely accused to be thrown in jail
And then he can give both back to him
He can give his reputation back
He can give kingdom to him
Authority to him
Both of those came back to him
So this is up to Allah Azza wa Jalla
And when we think of Allah as al-malik
Some of these things have to be kept in mind
But I want to dig into al-malik
Some more than even some of the other names
So when you think of the concept of kingdom
What are some thoughts that come in your mind?
First of all is its vastness
You know, a kingdom is only a kingdom
That's one square kilometer
It's not really a kingdom
But how large is the empire?
How big is the kingdom?
Like the British empire, for example, at some time
You know?
Or the Spaniards when they expanded at some point
Right, the Roman empire
Before them
The Egyptians
The great Egyptian empire
You think of their vastness
Like even Allah mentions this concept of vastness of kingdom
When the Pharaoh spoke in the Quran
Pharaoh says
Do I not alone own the kingdom of Egypt?
So what's he referring to?
The vastness of the kingdom
Now, we're doing this biha valla
With the word king
So when we think of Allah's kingdom
One thing we should think about
Is the vastness of Allah's kingdom
The size, the expanse of Allah's kingdom
You know, when I walk into
When I fly into Germany
I have to show my passport
To be able to enter this kingdom
Give it whatever name
Governance, sovereign nation
Right?
But I have to
And I have to now observe the laws that apply here
The driving rules that apply here
If I go to England where everything is wrong
Then I have to drive on the wrong side
And the car, you know, everything's wrong
But I have to do that because that's what's right there
Okay?
So the idea is
When you walk in, you are under the rule
The territorial rule of that kingdom
And then there are signs, right?
There are, you know, the manifestations of its might
Police, military
The monuments, the castles
The military arsenal
So Allah, as it would just say
Is that people that like to show off their power
Like the Americans like to show off their power
With, you know, the flag and the eagle
And a machine gun or whatever
That's their thing
That's their symbols of power, right?
Military might
Right? A militant nation
Well, you know
Allah describes Nimrud, for example
Who like to show off his power, right?
Allah, in the hadjah
Ibrahim, if you're a prophet, Allah will give you the power
Didn't you see the one who debated against Ibrahim, alayhis salam
Only because Allah had given him kingdom
He wants to show off how powerful he is
He's going to kill someone whoever he wants
He's going to let somebody live
Right?
Demonstration of his might
By the way, interestingly
The most powerful, sustained, powerful nations
Don't like to show off their might
The nations that are truly powerful
They don't have to show it
People recognize it anyway
But they don't have to do it
You know, the nations that are unstable politically
You know what they have to do?
They have to keep reminding their people
Who's in charge
So they have to keep putting a picture of their king
Or the ruler in every place
So, hey, don't forget, that's your king
Okay, before you go to the bathroom
You just say hi to the king and then go to the bathroom
You know, so
They have to do that because
There's no recognition of that power
It has to be forced on the people
But when a kingdom is stable
When a kingdom is stable
You don't have to have flags in your face all the time
You don't have to have the reminder
Of who the king or the authority is
You don't have to do that because
It's already the manifestation of its power
Is actually how smooth the kingdom is running
Almost as though
In political science
The government that is the most invisible
Is the most powerful
You know that?
And the government that's the most visible
Meaning you have to bring the armies out
And the tanks out on the street
And you have to have soldiers going down the street
That shows you how weak that government has become
Because they cannot control their nation
You understand?
If you think about it from those perspectives
On the one hand, Allah's kingdom is very obvious
The entire universe is Allah's kingdom
But Allah not enforcing His rule in the most visible way
You know, Allahid wa al-Baltin
Which was taught to us in Surat al-Hadeed
Is actually one of the ways you can think about
The manifestation of Allah's power
Allah is so powerful
He doesn't have to become visible
In how He exerts His power
Lotif al-Lima yasha
He's subtle in how He does things
Delicate in how He does things
Nearly unnoticed in how He does things
You know?
And some things is very obvious
And some things is very delicate and invisible
And that's actually one of the great manifestations
Of the might of Allah Azza wa Jalla
Here's what's coming up in the next episode
And this deeper look of Surat al-Jumu'ah
There are two kinds of ayat in the Quran
There are ayat all around us
And there are ayat of His revelation
But they both go...
They are valuable because they are ayat of the king
Just like the king of the...
The cup of the king in the Surat