Because usually, when you're trying to convert people to a new religion,
you're trying to get the least knowledgeable people
because they're easier to convert.
So you might go into the villages where the very poor people are,
give them some food,
and then invite them to your little religious gathering and easy to convert.
Which is by the way, some religions do that nowadays too.
Right?
But they won't go to the cultural capitals or the learning capitals.
They're not going to go to the universities, you see?
This is one of the things that makes Islam unique.
The Quran wasn't challenging the people who know the least of the other religion.
The Quran was inviting the people who know the most of the other religion.
Alhamdulillah.
Everyone once again, day four.
We move on from the two core ayaat of the surah,
the first two ayaat of the surah now.
And the third ayaat of this surah is actually grammatically connected to the second ayaat.
So this happens in the Quran where you may have multiple ayaas,
but actually there's still one sentence.
Right?
The easiest example of that is Alhamdulillah,
Maniki and Mindin is actually one sentence.
Grammatically it's one sentence.
Similarly,
is actually one sentence.
It's not multiple sentences.
So there are multiple ayaat, but there's still just one sentence.
So the same thing happens here is actually from the previous ayaa.
You notice, grammar students will notice the first word here is
which is not in the rafa form.
It's not aaharun.
Had it been aaharun, you could argue that this
is a new sentence.
But because it's monsoob, the nusb condition of it is impacted by something that came before.
And this might sound alien to some of you that haven't studied a little bit of Arabic grammar
or Arabic studies.
And my intention is also to make you curious about how do you figure that stuff out.
It's really not that hard.
And inshallah you'll get there.
By the end of the program, I'll show you a pathway you can take to get there,
inshallah, on your own.
Anyway, so wa ahadinaminhum, a rough translation.
Then we'll get into the dafsir matters.
And there are others.
And then there's the complicated phrase, others from them.
There are yet others from them.
Now, what does that mean?
There are more people other than the book, you know, the ones that he purified,
the ones that he read the ayaat to, the ones that he teaches the law and the book,
the law and the wisdom to, right?
There are yet and those are the ummiyeen.
Yet there are others from them.
Or
لما يلحقوا بههم that have not yet joined them.
They haven't joined them yet.
What does that mean?
They're about to.
What is with عزيز with حكيم?
And he is the ultimate authority and all wives.
That's the rough translation of the ayaat.
We're going to start with some commentary today.
I'm going to read some things to you that I think you should be exposed to.
And here's just some insights from different scholars like
ابن عاشور رحمه الله in his التحريب التنويل.
This is an unseen prediction.
Meaning the Quran has given a prediction of the future to the Prophet
صلى الله عليه وسلم that this message and this invitation of the
Prophet صلى الله عليه وسلم is going to reach other nations that are not Arab.
فارس والأرمن والأكراد والبربر والسودان.
You can tell these are different names of nations right?
والروم والتورك والتطار والمهول والصين.
Anyone know what is China?
China والهنوط.
Anyone know what is this?
The Indians the Tatars the Persians the the the the Armenians the
Barbar the Sudanese the Romans the Turks the Tatars then وغيرهم
and even beyond them وهاذة من معجزات القرآن من سنف الأخبار بالمغيبات
and this is part of the miracles of the Quran.
One of the miracles of the Quran that Allah told the Prophet صلى الله عليه وسلم
of how international this religion is going to be others
beyond them are going to be joining that haven't joined them yet.
وفي الآية دلالة على عمومي رسالة ابن بي صلى الله عليه وسلم
يجمير الأمم and in this ayah there is evidence this serves as an evidence of how universal
the prophethood of our prophet is صلى الله عليه وسلم for all nations.
You see so far Allah has sent prophets up until Muhammad صلى الله عليه وسلم
Allah sent prophets to particular nations right?
Messengers came to particular nations with a mission and they weren't sent to all of humanity
like they have to be concerned with all of humanity.
The closest to that you get in the history of the world is Ibrahim
عليه السلام but even he wasn't sent to all nations he was concerned for all nations
there's a difference right?
And he made a dua for all nations and he wanted to help all nations
but he wasn't sent as a mission to all nations but our messenger صلى الله عليه وسلم
his mission began with the region in which he was born and raised
رسولة منهم فيهم رسولة منهم we saw that
but then even before his life came to an end in this world
then he already instructed how the mission is supposed to now become beyond the borders of
the Arabs right?
So Islam starts spreading outside of that hijaz region outside of that desert even within
his own lifetime he's engaging with outside territories and this was part of the plan of
Allah and he's hinting at that plan inside
وَاَاَصْلَيْنَا مِنْهُمْ لَمْمَا يَلْحَقُوبِهِمْ فَهُوَنْ عَزِيزُ الْحَكِيمِ
Okay so now we're going to rediscuss something because this is connected to the previous
ayah we're going to rediscuss the concept of al-ummiyeen so far I told you these are
the unlettered uneducated people people that didn't have knowledge of the scripture
we're going to read some more things about them
وَاَصْلَجَ الْبُقَارِيْ وَاَمْسْلِمْ وَاَبُدَاوُدْ وَالْنِسَائِيْ عَنِبْنِ عُمرَ عَنِنَّ بِيْصَظَ اللَّهُمْ عَلِيْسَلَمْ قَالَ
This is a narration of the prophet sallallahu alayhi wa sallam is found in Bukhari and in Muslim
and this is Imam al-Aloosi al-Ruh al-Ma'ani quoting this I'll translate it for you
اِنَّ أُمَّةٌ أُمْمِيَةٌ لَا نَكْتُبُوا وَدَا نَحْسُبُوا
We are an ummah that is ummiya meaning the same word ummiyun we are a nation that is ummi
which means we don't write and we don't do calculations in other words we don't have
you know universities and we don't have these you know philosophical libraries and all that kind
of stuff we don't have that intellectual heritage of learning and learning institutions like the
Greeks had or some other civilizations had right so we're not those people but
and what is intended by that is that they are as though they just came out of their moms I mentioned
that to you before right uh
لم يتعلم الكتابة والحصاب they didn't learn advanced mathematics or writing
فهم على جبالتيهم الأولى they are on their original essential nature
فَالُمِّي نِسبَةٌ إِلَا الْأُمْ الَّتِيْ وَدَدَتُهُ
So ummi is associated with um so the e the e parted ummiyun the the extra y that you hear
that's called the yah ad nisbah and we use that in many cultures it came from the Arabs and a bunch
of us just kind of in different languages copied it so if you're from Pakistan you're what
Pakistani right if you're from Iran what are you
Iranian if you're from Afghanistan you're what
Avlani right so yeah be um so lots of languages took on this e as an adjective
so Afghanistan is a place but Avlani is an adjective right or hind is a place but hindi is
an adjective right so the same way there's the word umma and how do you make umma an adjective
ummi that's called yah ad nisbah so that's the yah ad nisbah here nisbah
اِلَا الْأُمْ الَّتِيْ وَدَتُهُ so it's attributing it to the the the one so
Avlani is the one of Afghanistan the one tied to Afghanistan ummi is the one tied to the mother
in that sense you see so that's that's where the meaning comes from what this button
اِلَا اُمْمَةِ العَرَبْ and it's also been said that this is referring to the the
nation of the Arabs meaning ummiyoon the people that belong to the Arab nation umma
وَقِلَا إِلَا اُمْمِ الْقُرَى that it's referring to the the nations or the the capital
of the nations because the ummiyoon may refer to the people of Makkah let me explain that really
quickly why why could that refer to the people of Makkah that you know the capital city in any
country we call it the capital uh the Arabs would call it the mother of all the cities
that's the mother city okay so ummul qurah so ummul qurah ummul qurah is one of the names of Makkah
okay why because it's the capital in a sense the cultural and economic capital of the region
right and the religious capital of the region so it's the um of all the other towns it's the
mother of all the other towns and that's that name is used in the Quran to describe Makkah
so actually Allah even describes that he sent messengers many times to different ummul qurah
meaning he sent them to cultural capitals because if you if you spread the message of Islam for
example Musa A.S. was sent in the cultural capital of Egypt right right at the palace of the Pharaoh
because if you impact there it will have impact everywhere and which is also true when you have
you know the cultural capitals have influence and if you can have if you can make it there then you
will your message will spread far and wide right so influencing Makkah or winning over Makkah will
not just have impact over Makkah it will have impact over all the regions and perhaps in this
there's also an indication that Islam wasn't just going to go into small villages and on the
peripheries Islam was going to go into the capitals of every civilization you know it was going to
go to the capitals of Europe the capitals of Africa the capitals of Asia and it was going to go to
the centers of society the centers of learning and have an impact there at the top because usually
when you're trying to convert people to a new religion you're trying to get the least knowledgeable
people because they're easier to convert so you might go into the villages where the very poor
people are give them some food and then invite them to your little religious gathering and easy
to convert which is by the way some religions do that nowadays too right but they won't go to the
cultural capitals or the learning capitals they're not going to go to the universities you see this
is one of the things that makes Islam unique the Quran wasn't challenging the people who know the
least of the other religion the Quran was inviting the people who know the most of the other religion
it was reverse engineering this entire proselytizing process i'll read something more to you
so this became a tough seer discussion among scholars does ummiyyeen refer only to the Arabs
because they were of course for for thousands of years they didn't have any learning or religion or
you know profits coming to them in that way so are they the ones that it's meant
so it has also been said that any people who did not have previous knowledge of the scripture or
they did not know about this final scripture they can be considered ummi too meaning al-ajab
meaning the non-arab also also he had that interpretation that ummiyyeen is not just
about the Arabs it's about all people that are uneducated the Quran by the way has a hint
towards that if if we think ummiyyeen are just the Arabs then Allah wouldn't have said about the
Israelites who are not Arabs he said about them
so which means the ummiyyeen are not just Arabs they're among them too
and this this opinion has also been criticized historically because the non-arabs were not
unlettered they were not uneducated the Chinese were in advanced civilization the Persians were
in advanced civilization the Romans were in advanced civilization how can you call them ummiyyeen
I would argue against this criticism and say this does not mean they didn't know engineering and
they didn't know how to build roads and highways and giant buildings and monuments this means they
didn't have knowledge of Allah's revelation that's what makes them ummiyyeen you can have a phd
nowadays in engineering and you can be very educated in the worldly sense and still be what from
a spiritual perspective you could still be an ummi you don't know much about the book right
and those people have some things in common like Allah says people like that they don't know the
book itself except they just have some wishes some hopes and then they have to build their religion
on assumptions they assume what they heard is true and they don't have any direct knowledge right
that's the that's the state of the ummiyyeen
another opinion is because ummi comes from umma that this just means they come from different
nations they just they just belong to different nations it's not talking about them not reading
and writing there's a narration from different hadith sources
Abū Hūrīlāzī says
we were sitting with the Prophet ﷺ when Surat al-Jumu'ah came down so they were sitting together
and the Prophet received this surah and he started reciting it so he read it
because the ayah said that the Sahabah are listening and the Prophet recites these words
that we're studying now
one of the men said to the Prophet ﷺ
who are these people who haven't joined us
now so who are these people that haven't joined us when so he was curious
so the Prophet ﷺ put his hand on Salman al-Fārīsī
Salman al-Fārīsī is from where
it's from Persia right so it's from Persia
okay
had faith was a treasure that was hiding in the Pilates constellation in the sky
constellation in the sky called Pilates
so the Arabs were really big on the stars
some of you that may have heard my Surat al-Najm series in Ramadan
may have noticed the Arabs talked a lot about the stars
so this hadith is referring to the Pilates constellation
and at night the Arabs were very keen on that particular constellation
so if imā and if faith was all the way to Thorayah
people like this this kind of person these kinds of people would have reached that too
what he's saying is look at the journeys he took to find imā
and if you study the story of Salman al-Fārīsī
you'll know the kind of incredible journey he took to find this message
right and the religious turns he took and the the turmoil he went through
traversing the world to try to find the final Prophet ﷺ
and to find his imā
so he's saying these people would have found faith no matter what
so he indicated according to this towards Persia
so he highlighted Persia
and it's clear that they're not ummiyīn of the Arabs
they're a different kind of ummiyīn
right now a lot of scholars when they discussed this they talked about
oh this this means because of this hadith the ummiyīn means the Persians
right the ummiyīn means the I would argue against that also
I would argue the Prophet ﷺ a lot of times to teach a lesson he gives an example
so what's a good example for you to understand who are these other people
what's the easiest example right there in the room
the soba al-Fārīsī you see this these kinds of people that doesn't mean oh the Persians only
no what it means is if this if this one came from the other side
so so much beyond the Arab territories how many more are there Allah didn't specify
and that's why so so
when Allah speaks in general terms he means general terms so it's actually referring to all nations
and the Persians are a specific category of them interestingly one of the things that's that's
got me really curious recently is just particularly Persia and the history of Persia the Farsi language
and Islam Farsi arguably has as much if not more Islamic literature in history than Arabic
and the scholars from around the world actually were producing their works in Arabic
and many of them were producing their works in in Farsi and even nowadays because you know because
of the Sunni Shi'a divide we think that when we think of Farsi we think of Shi'a literature or
something like that that is not the case historically at all actually the vast majority there's huge
volumes of literature that Muslims were were consuming the Seer works Hadith works Vik works
that were actually in in Farsi okay and there's a big big part of the and it didn't just come from
Iran is the crazy thing it was coming from all over the world and this became a part of the
Muslim heritage so the Muslim heritage is actually very multilingual one of the curiosities
I have in my own studies of the Quran I like to understand intellectual history also in other
words I know now because I come from the Indian Pakistani subcontinent background the people
there have a certain kind of thinking they have a certain kind of history they have they come from
a history of philosophy of music and poetry and they have that kind of and spirituality mysticism
you know they have that history and that impacted the way they looked at the Quran and they saw
things in the Quran that other other nations didn't see so they commented in a different way the Persians
have their own history of poetry and philosophy their own heritage and they were they were linguists
also they're very keen on language they were grammarians so when they come to the Quran they saw
something their interpretations of the Quran brought something new to the table and so the same
way the Andalusian scholars that were in Spain and the same way the African scholarship and the
same way you know scholarship for out from around the world because they have their own heritage and
culture then they're learning the Quran they're actually seeing things from different angles too
and they're bringing something more to the table right because they come from that heritage I'll
give you one example of that guys sorry for the interruption in the middle of this lecture
just before you continue I want to let you know and encourage you that I want you to sign up for
bayinatv.com and help other sign up or even sponsor students for bayinatv.com so we can create
worldwide communities of students that are studying the meanings and the benefit and the wisdom of the
Quran and are inshallah Ota'ala spreading that in their own circles thanks so much I'll give you
one example of that when you study when I studied the Arab tafasir right and the the tafasir that
come from Arab lands predominantly the one thing you will notice more than anything else is there's
a lot of focus on the word on every word there's a lot of focus right and it's in if you guys are
university students it's like micro studies yeah it's micro studies and then when you start studying
some Persian literature or some Urdu literature some subcontinental literature you'll notice
there's a lot of focus on the bigger picture they're saying okay what about this whole surah
where are we getting from the whole surah what about the whole page what about these
entire like they're they're zooming out what's that called it's macro studies right it's it's
there's a macro perspective there's a micro perspective and there's a macro perspective
and the the analogy I like to give is if you are a photographer and you're flying with a helicopter
over a valley and you take a really beautiful photo of the valley does that have value yeah of
course you captured a gorgeous scene but the helicopter lands and you zoom in on one flower
and one petal of that one flower and a bee sitting on that one petal of that one flower
and you take a picture does that have value also is that artistic also yeah it's the same
it's the same camera it's the same location but you can zoom in and you can zoom out and each one
of them has an advantage but each one of them has a disadvantage if you zoom out you miss the smaller
details and if you zoom in you miss the bigger picture and what's amazing about this umma is
that Allah did not restricts this umma's intellectual heritage to one culture so all these different
cultures with their own kind of you know like Germans are notoriously scientific in their thinking
and mathematical in their thinking right so imagine German scholarship on Islam right German
scholarship on Islam I know I know there's a lot of non-muslim German scholarship on Islam I know
that's existed for a couple of centuries actually I've read some of it too in translation I mean
do you remember German um but uh there's French scholarship on Islam there's Spanish scholarship
on Islam there's and I'm curious about you know different cultures scholarship on Islam and what
they brought to the table what they saw that other people just don't they don't have that lens so they
can't see it right and this is one of the great gifts that Allah gave to our religion you know you
might be fascinated to know this Allah said ahadin all others will join them you think others okay so
few more will join actually the majority of the umma is Arabs the minority is Arabs the vast majority
of the umma is actually non-Arabs and that happened very early on extremely early on they're the
nucleus but that it just spread and kept on spreading and spreading and spreading the analogy of
Islam is like a seed right you plant a seed a tree grows but the tree has lots of fruits that
those fruits have seeds those seeds spread and it just and it spread like almost like pollen
that's how it spread and I actually Allah gave the analogy of la idaha idvallah as a tree you know
you know the example of the tree the roots are deep and the branches go into the sky and that
analogy is pretty amazing because actually that's kind of what happened in the world with Islam
you know we traveled like the wind we traveled everywhere and we just spread and spread and
spread so I I say this not just because it's a cool observation I have a request from all of you
you're all many of you are from different heritage different backgrounds right and when you
you know you you modernize and you you know the world moves forward and we have to learn the
language in which we can get a job and we can we have to learn the language of the university
a lot of times the younger generation loses the mother language right so for example I speak Urdu
but then I was most of my adult life I was in in the United States so I didn't speak Urdu much
right and then I started losing touch with Urdu and the only when I started getting back into
Islam I said okay I'm gonna read the Arabic if I see but I'm also gonna read Urdu literature
so at least I have two civilizations I have access to right so I started reading Urdu materials a
lot too so that kept me in touch with Urdu but while living in New York and living in Texas
I'm keeping in touch with my Urdu then after 30 years I went back to Pakistan 29 years to be exact
so I haven't been back for 29 years I go back and I start speaking and a young man came to me and
said you speak old people Urdu he literally said you speak Nawabi Urdu and I was like huh
and the reason he said that is because in those 30 years what happened to the Urdu language
it deteriorated it actually declined and so the amazing literature in Urdu that
your grandmother could appreciate or even I could appreciate I'd say like a grandma now but yes
now the next generation has less contact with it you you understand I think it's as important
learning the Arabic language is number one but alongside it whatever heritage you come from
you should master that language you shouldn't just speak it to just casually hang out you should
actually know its heritage its legacy especially if you're lucky enough to know something about Farsi
or you know the languages in which Muslims have a heritage Muslims have a history if
if Muslims have been in the region for a couple of hundred years or more then there's a scholarly
history in that literature in that in those works and you can bring that out you can expose that to
the rest of the world you know to the rest of the umma so they may be able to benefit anyway so
the aakhirin amin hum lammayal haqoobihim they haven't yet joined them lammayal just this is a small
grammar note manfiyu ha mus'tamir ilal hal this is a word and it means negative but negative up until
now wa yutawakka'u wukooruhu ba'dahu and it's expected that it will happen right after so just
like you say hey it has it has it's not come yet not yet there's an expectation that he's coming
right so Allah has set the expectation that more Muslims are now coming that are not from among the
Arabs this is about to get bigger and bigger and bigger okay this is really cool also al
al-yalhaqoobihim alhaqoobihim is joined is translated as they haven't joined them yet that's how
he translated it they haven't joined them yet but al-ahik bin al-thimar is actually this word is used
for fruits that come on the same tree one season after another season after another season so the
you know the next season's fruit the next season's fruit that's called al-ahik min al-thimar which is
really awesome because now we're being described as new fruits from the same tree right so the tree
starts with the sahaba it's the same tree and then newer and newer fruits are emerging with every
season and we're just another season of those fruits but the tree we belong to the same exact
tree it's such a beautiful connection to our history to these people that Allah has made you
know nations they pride themselves on their own history right and now because of after colonialism
there's a lot of you know because we're all nation states now right so you know you have a region
where they're all geographically actually very close to each other culturally they're close to
each other language wise they're close to each other but the the British or the French or the
you know the day not the Danes but the Dutch or whoever they'll come and draw a line and say okay
you guys are Malaysian you guys are Indonesian okay you guys are Pakistan you guys are India you
guys are Bangladesh you guys are Sri Lanka you guys they'll draw these lines right and it's been it
hasn't even been a hundred years since those lines but people now identify themselves inside these
lines right and then there's national pride and your flag and if there's a sport if there's a
match going on and everybody's waving their flag you know that kind of thing but what Allah did
is so remarkable that he actually joined us to people that we don't have any genetic connection to
we don't even have a geographical connection to them we're not even from the same region the
Prophet sallallahu alaihi wa sallam is in hijaz and the Indonesian is on the other side of the world
and they're connected and they're bonded together and that bond is thicker than blood
it's thicker than blood and you know like the the the tree that gives a fruit right the fruit is
almost identical from the previous year's fruits it's the same it's not a different fruit it's the
same fruit it's a new manifestation of the fruit the only time the fruit goes bad is if there's not
enough water not enough sun something went bad right but the potential to produce amazing fruit
is always there isn't it so the idea inside this analogy is also that as generations go by it's not
like oh Muslims are just going to be a inferior product the good ones are all dead and the new ones
are you know the all the amazing Muslims died and us losers are the only ones left you know this kind
of mentality is also problematic because Allah has acknowledged those who will be coming and joining
them and he did not make them feel make them seem inferior right or the other and I've said this in
previous lectures but it's important to note the Arabic language is such a deep part of the of Arab
culture just like or do or Farsi or Bahasa or you know Swahili or Senegalese are part of their own
culture but Arabic Allah took it from the Arabs and he said you can't keep it for yourself you can
have it but I'm gonna make this the language of the entire Oma they're all gonna have it they're
all gonna share it so you don't have to be Arab to be Arab you just have to know Arabic
in the Arab listen Arabs are just a tongue that's all it is no other language oh once you speak it
you're that person not really you can speak German you can act German but you're not German
you know like it was pretty funny I was one time I was in back in the day I was in New York I was
taking a walk it was a big it's a big Russian neighborhood and I clearly don't look Russian
and this guy and he didn't even speak English properly he's a Russian dude
but he's just steady he can't stand that I'm walking by this Russian neighbor he goes
go back to your country let's go together okay now we have to this this idea of others joining
we have to learn something about Jewish studies Hebrew studies that is going to help us gain
some perspective about this Ia I told you that in this Surah the word Quddus right the word Yuzaki
him there are other implications that this is actually there's a secondary audience which is some
some some of the factions of the rabbis right not all of them but some of them so we're gonna
read some things from some rabbinic attitudes towards Gentiles and the Goyim this is courtesy
of Dr. Sakit Hossain who's a dear friend and colleague of mine who's finished his PhD out of
Oxford in biblical studies Alhamdulillah he's a scholar of the Quran and he's also
has mastered the Hebrew language and has studied the Torah and Jewish scholarship pretty extensively
and writes about the correlation between the two so I and he's on my WhatsApp so I can flex that so
I just say hey bro I gotta give can you give me a non-phd version because I gotta talk to humans
so then he'll just send me like so this is from WhatsApp messages is the the truth okay the source
and concerning bloodshed in what matters is the so this is about this is their fatawa on killing
in their literature a non-ju against a non-ju and a non-ju against a ju is liable a ju against a
non-ju is exempt meaning if a member of the Israelites kills a non-ju it's not a crime
they're exempt okay and concerning theft in in what matter is the transgressors capable
in case of kidnapper a thief the one who seizes a beautiful war captive you see where that's going
and the like a non-ju against a non-ju and a non-ju against a ju is prohibited a ju against a
non-ju is permitted so there was this idea that these people you can do anything you want with them
in some of their groups not all of them but some of them developed this idea that us the believers
they saw themselves as the believers we can do anything with these kufar they're basically less
than human right which should sound scarily familiar because there are some muslims you if
if i just change the words muslim and non-muslim is from ju lanju you would think this is some
some muslims that are saying this nowadays right this the source of it is the tosefta it's one
of the earliest rabbinic texts along with the mishnah this was written around 200 bc the the
source the chapter is called bodh azadah which means outsider worship which is a chapter within it
okay let's keep going why are the gentiles impure meaning why are non-ju is impure uh in their in
their mind why are the kufar impure okay some rabbinic writings several classical jewish reports
give the view that the serpent who tempted even the garden actually copulated with her that's
weird but yes that's actually their interpretation which is why humanity is tainted by sin this is
similar to the christian idea of original sin but then israel is standing at mount syni Israel
in standing at mount syni had their filth cease non-jews who did not stand at the mount syni
did not have their filth cease when they stood at mount syni i told you the account that the
Quran describes the conversation this is their version of that conversation their version among
some of them the conversation is when they stood at mount syni they were forever purified and
everybody else they're not just their filth did not end actually they believe human beings are born
filthy because the children of adam are actually how what it was not with adam how what was with
the serpent that's what they're basically saying so this is their the jewish version in some rabbinic
traditions of original sin we don't believe in original sin they have that concept right the
general rule in early Judaism was that the categories of pure and not pure did not apply to
jews by the time you get to the Talmud which is completed around the sixth century there is much
harsher view in which Gentiles are considered impure uh so and this is some more details we
don't have to get into the details but let's go back to why i brought all of this up
Allah says
ummiyyin is basically their equivalent of non-jews Gentiles which they by definition consider what
what do they consider them impure he says he raised among the impure and from their perspective
and then what does he say about them he purifies them
what you say key him you see what's happening here their view was what so long as you're under
the mountain you are purified unless saying no the only thing that will purify you is the word of Allah
and this messenger is coming to the ummiyyin and he's purifying them and in this next slide
that we're studying now and by the way the only people who can access the Torah and access the
word of God are the most pure people but now these ummiyyin that are supposedly impure not only are
they getting purified now that he's going to teach them the the Quran the book he's gonna teach them
the book the purest of all scriptures he's gonna teach them that so now there's a shift in the
definition of purity purity is not coming from a certain race like in certain classes of hinduism
certain races certain classes of people are pure people and certain others are then it right
they're the untouchables they are the the the lower classes this didn't just happen in in in one
civilization there are many uh in korea in china in india there are many class societies where if
you're born into a certain kind of class you will remain in that class you cannot come out of that
class you are you are born into impurity you're born into it and you have to escape it somehow
right and the the christians even adopted it as a doctrine all human beings are born into sin
they're born dirty they're born impure and only through the blood of jesus can they be purified
and quran comes along it says no no no no hold on this is all made up the truth is every human being
is born pure fitlidallah that the fatala nasa adiha and the corruption comes at the hands of people
you weren't designed impure you were designed pure it's a it's a fundamentally different definition
than what you're getting in other religious traditions and by the way it those of you that
are students of psychology this is an interesting small fact if you believe human beings are
fundamentally impure born into sin lower class whatever you're born into sin then you are
from the beginning broken you're broken from the beginning and you just have to spend your life
identifying how you can undo the damage that's un inevitable you're already damaged right and
when you study Freudian psychology which is the father of modern psychology right you will notice
that that the definition of human beings they're bored they're born with certain essentially
psychological defects we're all basically disturbed subconsciously and i won't spell out how we're
disturbed if you're going to study Freud you'll know for yourself and then it's manifesting further
down the road as now in you know pop psychology pop psychology means anybody on twitter becomes a
therapist you know let me tell you how to deal with your emotions right everybody's a counselor
everybody's a therapist everybody's licensed to i love life coaches i love these guys are amazing
like certified certified life coach the the the the most entertaining ones are the muslim ones
certified good believer that and what's there you know how people put reviews underneath
the review is this is a really good person it's like oh okay
but the idea in all of these kinds of brands of therapy and i'm actually a very eager student
of psychology and i appreciate the science is that oh you were probably traumatized by this
or that or the other and you're still dealing with your trauma and you haven't healed and you're just
going to spend your life undoing the effects of the trauma and everybody walks out of therapy like
yep i'm a traumatized victim i'm i'm just i'm just trauma walking around and then you go you go
somewhere you go to your coffee place and the guy takes two extra minutes to bring your coffee
i'm traumatized by this late delivery and i got triggered and you're just you're just living in
trauma right but the the the quran's argument actually is that you were born pure and then dirt
came on and then when revelation comes the dirt comes off again you's a key him where you are
leaving the book about what hit about profound difference okay now why is this important that
means all nations are now equally blessed there's no more one blessed ethnicity the you know the the
the all the african nations are blessed all the australians are blessed the aborigines are blessed
the native americans are blessed the europeans are blessed there's no better or worse nation they're
all now equal because akharid i'm in home covers everybody all nations are now an extension of the
ummeyin which means the ummeyin didn't know any better and they could be purified you could have
been living in a society where there's thousands of years of shit doesn't matter you can be purified
too you're just just like them and purity is no longer about a special class or a lineage
you're not born royal you're not born special everyone's born special and purity is about
what you do with your life after that okay so now this this was just a few things about that
ayah well i'm in home let me have hope will be him i will just add one more thing as we as we
start this second this next ayah which is that you know Allah made us an umma that could not
distinguish between which race we come from and yet at the same time Allah says
he made you into nations and tribes so you can get to know each other and there's an interesting
tidbit there about shuroban shuroban arabic shab means people in modern arabic shab means people
but shab in old arabic actually used to mean a hole in the wall sometimes you have a wall it's got a
little crack in it or a hole in it and what do you have to do you have to fill it up right
shab are called people but not perfect people they have a hole they have some kind of crack
and some other shab have a different kind of crack and some other shab have a different kind of crack
and when you meet other people you're like i can learn something from you that i can fill my gap my
crack with there's a crack in my wall that i can fix by learning from you and you can learn something
for me that can fix the crack in your wall so when when believers have cultural exchange they learn
from each other they actually better each other and Allah designed this system of just a a bunch of
nations that have many strengths and some weaknesses and somebody's weakness is somebody else's what
strength and it's just this thing of beauty Allah created right which is kind of what i was saying
even in our intellectual histories in it there's a micro view but the micro view has one disadvantage
that you don't get the macro picture so there's these are one shab they have this kind of view
not another shab have that kind of view you know you were able to merge between the two of them
shawab and the tribes that you know
Salamu Alaikum everyone there are almost 50,000 students around the world
that are interested on top of the students we have in studying the Quran and its meanings
and being able to learn that and share that with family and friends and they need sponsorships
which is not very expensive so if you can help sponsor students on bayna tv please do so and
visit our sponsorship page i appreciate it so much and pray that Allah gives our mission success
and we're able to share the meanings of the Quran and the beauty of it the world over